no introduction needed here I'm fat
you're fat we're all fat let's talk
about fat the different types and how
much of each you need to be eating so
before we do that we got a cop talk
about a few things number one what's the
fact really do you may or may not know
that it's actually very important to
structure so all of yourselves for the
most part have what's called a
phospholipid and lipid is pretty similar
to fat bilayer membrane which means
their cell walls keep them together are
made of fat
of course it's it's an energy producer
which is what we're going to talk about
today in bulk it's you're also required
for a bunch of fat absorption digestion
and transportation so we call these fat
soluble vitamins in other words if
you're gonna take some supplemental
vitamin D it's probably important to do
it when you eat fat because we need fat
to take the deed
like I said transport it in the ground
so it's really important for a bunch of
vitamin things it's also the backbone of
your hormone production so in other
videos we'll talk about how you can use
things like cholesterol to then make
testosterone and so if you are then
extremely low on fat you're probably
gonna have some hormonal dysregulation
or potentially skin hair things like
that are also made from that of course
it does temperature regulation right see
that everyone knows that if you have a
little bit of extra fat especially
around the adipocyte though the
underneath the skin etc you can handle
colder temperatures a little bit better
and vice versa and then it's also does
what I call quarantine ii and i thought
based on the time i'm filming this in
June 2020 so the terms quarantine felt
nice here but really what I mean is if
you've got say toxins and don't go too
crazy with that word but what fat can do
is it can sequester them so you can
store these toxins if you want in the
fat and tell you how proper time to
digest them and urinate them out or or
get rid of them in some other fashion
I'm also a potential problem because you
may not realize they're still in you and
then they could come leaking out later
but nonetheless so I guess the point I
wanted to make with all this is people
tend to think about nutrition or fat in
regard to how much do I eat etcetera but
they don't really realize what else is
doing and we've also then that's because
we've demonized fat a lot
the logic is clear if I eat fat I get
fat but hopefully as I'll show you in a
second and all my numerous other videos
that I have that's not simply the case
ok so now the most basically to think
about fat is it's separated into either
unsaturated or saturated and we're gonna
go into these different categories what
they are explained how much you should
be eating of each and really I'll show
you the background of what they look
like and then why they function where
they function and I'll give you a little
bit of a spoiler here unsaturated fat is
not in quote-unquote bad for you any
excess of fact any excess of
carbohydrate any excess food ingestion
can lead to you getting over fat and
that's not great right so but but we
don't need to necessarily go on low-fat
diets so because of that we actually
probably should issue a bit of a formal
apology to fat I mean I certainly know
when I was in school it was very much
demonized don't eat fat low fat diets
etc and if you're paying attention at
all at the last 10 years that was
clearly very wrong fat is not inherently
extremely bad for you the probably the
reason it gets this bad rap is it does
have over two times the amount of
calories per gram that carbohydrates and
protein do so if you look at a giant
plate of food and you see a big pile of
chicken and you see an equal pile of
avocado the avocado is gonna have twice
the calories so if you ever looked at
the calories say in peanut butter this
is a classic example and you're like wow
you know a whole huge cup is not the 200
calorie serving size it's actually
really really really small so because
that people can accidentally eat more
calories and they realize when they eat
fat we eat more calories you may get fat
okay but if calories are either a fat is
eaten at a normal quantity or
inappropriate quantity they're not
extremely dangerous for you in fact
saturated fat has many many benefits
that we're gonna talk about and it
should be a part of your diet you don't
want to walk around consuming no amount
of saturated fat but we do want to keep
it in regulation just like we want to
keep everything and regulation okay so I
have a talk at length about this topic
but I want to get into the real beef of
today but
important note we have to make anytime
we talk about fat there's what we did
wrong there having said that just
because fat isn't inherently bad for you
it's probably not a good idea to walk
around and eat 15 pieces of bacon a day
there are some problems and there are
still some very clear poor health
associations with excessive saturated
fat right now again eating eating animal
fat eating saturated fat and his natural
state is fine but just like anything
else quantities should be measured right
and 15 pieces of bacon a day is not a
reasonable approach you're gonna get too
much saturated fat and I don't care what
people that are ridiculous and in huge
ideologues and zealots of ketosis will
tell you if you eat too much fat you
will get fat period there's no
discussion there right now it's not
again it's not nearly as bad as we
thought it was that doesn't mean it's a
free pass either and I have a lot more
thoughts on that topic of course but
like I said I want to move on to the
beef of what we're getting into today so
the basic way that we store fat in our
body whether it's visceral or
subcutaneous so visceral being kind of
around your core if you will may be
packed around your liver etc and
subcutaneous being underneath your skin
okay we call that all kind of adipose
tissue those are typically stored as
what we call tri glycerine tri meaning
three in bliss right so you can see here
these circles in each circle is a carbon
atom so just like carbohydrates
triglycerides are made primarily of long
chains of carbon and this is why we
think we term things like organic
chemistry basically the study of carbon
all life is really comes down to that
and so here's what happens triglycerides
form a fancy e structure okay so it has
those three red circles which are what
we call the glycerol backbone so that's
actually a three carbon three carbon
carbohydrate called glycerol and then
each one of these chains coming
horizontally off each carbon from the
glycerol backbone is a fatty acid chain
okay so when you put those three fatty
acid chains together on the backbone of
the glycerol we get a tri bliss right
and that's
we store them in our body plants do the
same thing other animals store it the
same way when we go to metabolize this
fat for energy or for fuel we have to
break that down the glycerol goes into
its own piece and in fact the glycerol
can be converted into glucose if you'd
like and then we can actually start
chopping these fatty acid chains down a
couple of carbons at a time that's
called beta oxidation
I've got separate videos going through
all this in detail if you want to look
around but nonetheless these fatty acids
are broken down a couple of carbons at a
time that energy is released and we get
that and this is why for example if you
compare this to carbohydrates which
typically have six carbons total and a
triglyceride as you're clearly saying
has far more than six you can get way
more energy per gram of fat than you can
per gram of carbohydrate again it's over
twice as much nine grams per cake house
per gram versus about four for
carbohydrate now the fatty acid chains
themselves don't typically get stored as
carbohydrate so you can't really do that
but again the glycerol backbone at least
we think the glycerol backbone
definitely can if you break down a
triglyceride put in the bloodstream
don't end up using it instead of being
converted to carbohydrate it'll probably
just gets what's called re esterified
and restore it back as an adipose tissue
okay so this is just a visual of what's
happening there again I put a number in
each one and so in this particular case
there are twelve carbons per fatty acid
chain now as you'll see in a second the
number actually can be quite
dramatically different so fatty acid
chains are typically somewhere in the
neighborhood of 12 to 22 carbons long
but they can certainly be as low as six
and far higher that's in human nutrition
though that's mostly what we're talking
about is 12 to 22 carbon in length of
the fatty acid chain now within a
triglyceride not all fatty acid chains
have to be equal so in this example they
are they're all three 12 carbon lengths
but it could be twelve and then ten and
an eighth or something like that
okay now the length of each carbon in a
fatty acid chain is what determines what
type of fatty acid we call it and I'll
show you examples in a second and I know
you've heard of some of them and you may
not realize
oh that's what that term means okay so
another way to think about it is this
we typically classify the fatty acid
chains as me as short medium long and
very long and you can see the numbers
that would you know denote those
qualifications of those qualifications
here but like I said the medium to long
chain fatty acids are by far the most
abundant in both plant and animal
sources and so for human nutrition
that's really what we're talking about
now some other videos of made there's
actually a long one on called I think
why you fart so much or something like
that you can see actually where short
chain fatty acids come from it's
actually can be a result of carbohydrate
digestion yeah that's right the special
bacteria in your large intestines can
actually metabolize special types of
carbohydrates and as a byproduct of that
give out short chain fatty acids okay
you may also if you're into ketosis I
want to look more of that stuff you'll
start to see short chain medium chain
fatty acid stuff being important for
those types of use and then there are
again the very long-chain fatty acids as
well which are more than the 22 I
thought the medium and long chain if you
also watch some of metabolism and
performance based videos I have and I've
probably covered this in at least three
to five videos you can see the
functional and important differences
between say the short and medium chain
fatty acids and the long and very long
in terms of how we metabolize them for
energy how some can be very effective
for performance some are less effective
and how that all rolls up also explains
things like putting large chunks of
coconut butter or other or super fatty
things in your coffee
why all that stuff happens and I'll give
you a spoiler the short and medium
chains get to do a special trick through
the brain and the mitochondria that long
chains don't get too so anyways point is
important functional differences between
them so let's go back the beginning here
and let's talk a little bit more about
saturated specifically and then we'll go
into unsaturated and I'll finish here
with some examples of how much to eat so
the way that you can typically tell that
a fat is saturated is whether or not
it's solid at room temp
so if you think think at things like
think of things like butter coconut oil
meat these are all gonna be solid
they're not liquid form I'm here again
you can see on the other slide some of
the different examples of the different
types of butter butyric acid lauric acid
palmitic acid stearic acid those are all
very very common that you would see if
you want to memorize these things that's
fine I'm just trying to highlight the
fact that when the lengths of the
carbons are different in a chain we call
it something different and all of those
examples with exception of milk but it's
not hard to see cheese and yogurt and
things like that are solid at room
temperature okay if we contrast that to
the image I showed you before this is
actually what the triglycerides look
like so you can see the blue part over
there of the vertical blue and what
you're actually seeing are those three
carbon chains like I talked about and
because the chemistry reasons the
carbons have to have a hydrogen which is
what that H is at the end okay so you
have the three carbon backbone glycerol
backbone and then you have the different
lengths of carbons coming out
horizontally the top one there you can
see is saturated and it's palmitic acid
so it's got its 15 carbons there the
next one down stearic acid of 17 and
it's also saturated but take a look at
the third one this is Alea Kassadin it's
go but we call mono unsaturated still
have 17 carbons like stearic acid but
look at what happens with that funky
corner okay so that funky corner is
important and it is the reason why it's
called mono unsaturated but before we
get there real quick I sort of forgot
with palmitic acid I wanted to give a
couple of examples but the pol Medic
acid is very very common
probably the most common fatty acid in
humans stearic acid you're gonna mostly
get from animals and coconuts etc and
the oleic acid is is olive oil in fact I
think depending on the olive oil
somewhere between 50 and 80 percent of
olive oil is actually made up of oleic
acid so it's very very very high in
unsaturated fat okay so now going back
to here now the chemistry here is very
important because it determines both a
name and the function and I know you're
probably have been thinking hey
we've been told the saturated fats are
worse force and the unsaturated fats are
better and most people on the street
would say that it's not totally wrong
the question is why and that's what
we're going to answer so you can see
that it bends in there the reason it's
doing that is because it's got a double
carbon bond so look at where that arrow
is pointing you see how the carbon chain
in that Bend has two horizontal arrows
connecting it looks like an equal sign
well in chemistry organic chemistry that
signifies a double bond and the reason
it's double bond that is because it's
missing two hydrogen's you see below see
how all the other carbons have a
hydrogen above it and below it but these
two lack of hydrogen below it and so
because atoms like to be bonded and you
know you remember this from middle or
high school or something they don't like
to be unbalanced think of this way the
things that hang out from the bottom of
the carbon and say there's nothing here
and so we'll just go sideways and link
up so we're all at least balanced what
this does is cause a bend in the chain
and also works exactly like da knows in
terms of if you've ever played that game
you can't play on pieces that are
covered up on all sides right metabolism
is almost exact same way so because the
fact that it is not covered up right
there you can actually very easily get
in and start metabolizing the fatty acid
right there it's an opening and so now
the difference is between unsaturated
and saturated fat chemically have
functional significance and help one's
because of the pros and cons so for
example because unsaturated fats have
this opening if you will don't make it
and easier to metabolize they're
typically not stored as well state of
saturated fats store far better
unsaturated ones store worse they're
easier to metabolize they're easier to
burn for energy and so because of that
are less likely to make us over fat now
those are the same calories right or
less calories but the downside is with
saturated with unsaturated fats in this
case it's mono unsaturated that also
means they go rancid faster and so if
you're looking at this from the entire
I'll say eating circle if you're the
manufacturer you don't
make products that go rancid really fast
because you're gonna lose yourself it
doesn't have the shelf life in fact
people don't want it alright it's gonna
go bad and this is why things like olive
oil are far more expensive than things
like butter because they had or even
coconut oil is more expensive than olive
oil because it has to account for the
fact that it's going to be stable or not
stable they're gonna lose a lot of the
products they have to ship it colder
they have to make sure the bottle is and
not be able to be penetrated by light
etc so it's good for you but it's more
expensive so there are pros and cons
inside your body that's the same thing
there are cons to having good storage
ability to store backup energy this is
one of the major benefits of having
again stored fat having fat on you is
not necessarily a bad thing we just
don't want to be over fat ok so to kind
of recap what I just said a saturated
fat means that a zero double cup double
carbon bonds in any of its fatty acids
so going back here all those carbons
have one bond they don't have that equal
sign unsaturated they'll have at least
one double carbon bond in at least one
of its fatty acids now you can continue
that down and say also what this really
means is a saturated fat has is not
missing any or is missing zero hydrogen
an unsaturated fat is missing two or
more
okay so unsaturated fats are unstable in
other words easy to metabolize but go
rancid fat where saturated fats are
stable they store well but why was that
again I'm quizzing you why were the
saturated fats better
that means story that's right because
they're not missing that hydrogen bond
so they're harder to metabolize oxygen
has a more difficult time if you
remember from some of the other videos
fat metabolism is a hundred percent
aerobic there's no anaerobic component
to it so it requires oxygen by the same
token if you put fat in an environment
that has access to oxygen like leaving
your your olive oil open it will start
to metabolize and go rancid really
really really quickly the same is true
for things like walnuts or other even
whole foods that are
and unsaturated fat they go rancid
really quick so you got to keep them in
cool dark places don't expose them to
air don't expose in the wine they go bad
fast
well things like your margarine you
could leave out on the table and it
might it might melt but it's probably
not gonna go rancid that fast you got a
long time cheese the same way bacon you
get it right okay so now these
unsaturated fats can be in what the form
of what are called modeling saturated or
polyunsaturated so in the oleic acid
example a olive oil one I showed you it
had one spot that was had a double
carbon bond there if it has more than
that so if there was a you know a break
and then another break somewhere then we
would call it a poly unsaturated fat
okay there are other types of
unsaturated fat called trans fats and I
know you're thinking trans fats those
the ones that are bad for me yes but
they're unsaturated and people that
confuses a lot of people here's exactly
what happens so if we go back to our
slide here so remember our
monounsaturated fat the problem really
was it's got that double carbon bond
because it's missing two hydrogen's so
if I come in and I hydrogen eight or add
hydrogen's back to that I have taken an
unsaturated fat and made it a saturated
fat okay we call that process
hydrogenating and so in the case of
things like oil from soybeans we may
call this a partially hydrogenated
soybean oil this is exactly what happens
with trans fats and so why they're so
bad is because you're taking a naturally
mono or polyunsaturated fatty acid and
unnaturally forcing it into becoming a
saturated fat so something that's
supposed to have the properties of
unsaturated Pauline now the properties
of saturated and it causes a whole
litany of problems now you are in a good
spot because you generally don't have to
worry about that because trans fats are
no longer really legal now they're going
around them but trans fats for the most
part are one type of fat that almost no
one
disagrees with anymore in terms of it
being healthy right it is basically
unequivocally bad no one argues that
anyway so that's line dependent on you
that is exactly what happens with things
like margarine so if you look at
margarine that's something that I grew
up on in my generation probably more
margarine than they did butter because
it was cheaper and it's stored longer
right so what they did is they took the
little bit of unsaturated fat and
polyunsaturated fats and mono in butter
and they hydrogenated it or they made
butter from non butter things in this
particular example many margarine only
contain like you know 5 to 20% actual
butter the rest of it was other things
and so is a butter substitute we thought
it was better because it had
quote-unquote less fat but it actually
just had a boatload of trans fat and it
was terrible for us and so margarine if
you go to the stores now very hard to
find right compared to regular butters
whole fat or otherwise right but that's
in case you're wondering what partially
hydrogenated soybean oils actually I'm
and then to finish up here our last
category of unsaturated fats are what we
call the omega fatty acids so make a 3 6
& 9 these are what people typically call
fish oil I'm gonna make a separate video
probably a 25 minute or so on fish oil
specifically I'm going to everything
they're like I kind of just did how much
how it works what it really basically is
it cetera but the omega-3 in the omega
sixes are what some people will call the
essential fatty acid and so these are
ones that we need to kind of make sure
we consume in our diet if you look at if
you go watch with the protein videos
you'll see that there are some amino
acids are also essential but this is
really the only fat version of the
essential ones we need to get in our
diet so to finish up on some practical
recommendations here how much fat to eat
typically somewhere in the neighborhood
of all they're going to slide this down
20 to 35 percent of our total calories
but remember that actually means
probably half the volume of food on our
plate I made a separate video where I
showed you different food examples okay
I think it's I can't read the exact
title says carbs fats proteins what are
they really or something like that
but because the caloric amounts per size
is so much bigger the total volume needs
to be smaller right so uh no that number
can be of course if you're doing a
specific high-fat diet or something like
that of course it can go up of course
you can survive just fine on 60 70 80
percent fat of course you can I'm just
saying for most people normally who are
not on a specific ketogenic diet
probably somewhere in the neighborhood
of 20 to 35% of your calories from fat
is a very reasonable number with in
terms of saturated fat probably about a
third of your fat being saturated is
okay again you can go a little higher
but if you translate the math there that
means in the neighborhood of 10 percent
of your total calories coming from
saturated fat and I'll actually do this
universe you don't really want to be
lower than that you're probably going to
run into some hormonal problems if you
start getting a lot lower than that and
everything else is not in check you can
have problems potentially absorbing some
of these vitamins and some other things
so I wouldn't make sure that you're
minimizing saturated fats like a zero
just eat real Whole Foods and the fat
will totally probably be just fine in
terms of cholesterol guys remember that
that's a fat as well less than around
300 milligrams per day especially if
you're not very active if you are that
can go a little bit higher but we don't
need to go out of our way to eat
tremendous amount of cholesterol now of
course eating cholesterol didn't
necessarily mean cholesterol in your and
your arteries and stuff but there is
clearly a relationship there okay it's
not what we were once told but that
doesn't mean there's no relationship at
all either in terms of the Omega threes
some of the neighborhood one 1/2 grams
per day depending on which species you
are male or female and yeah it just
depends on what you're aiming for here
so if you're looking for like the
cardiovascular benefits etc now people
are not as hot on fish oil
supplementation as we used to be watch
this fish oil video for that but if
you're looking for the anti-inflammatory
benefits of them the numbers can be a
little bit higher so I think some more
then II would have two or so grams per
day two maybe a little bit higher
is still totally fine depending on what
you're going after health training high
volume low volume recovery peak
performance that's it but then you can
adjust with gold so fat is a pretty easy
one to adjust with your goal so if
you're trying to lose weight you cut a
little bit of fat out the calories
really come off it's very easy you don't
have to cut the food down nearly as much
likewise if you want to go up so a very
quick way if you're like madam under
calories because I'm training really
hard or I'm trying to gain muscle or I'm
a hard time eating just double up the
spoonfuls of almond butter and you'll
get 3 or 4 or 500 extra calories really
really quickly put a little bit of extra
oil on your food on your salad like this
comes real fast real easy so it's a very
easy one to adjust with your goals
hopefully that helped let me know in the
comments section what else under the
fount umbrella do you want me to talk
about what do you wanna be Claire
clarify you want me do another short
video longer one what do you want me to
go into share it around learn from that
and some of you I'll see you in class or
pseudo see you in class or see your quiz
at least on this or something the rest
of you I'll never see you ever probably
it breaks my heart
you
[Music]